Guide to the John Daniel Wild Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Daniel Wild papers
1934-1974
1957-1972
GEN MSS 842
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.59
(13 boxes)
The collection contains writings, lecture notes, syllabi, research notes and notebooks and other materials documenting the scholarly career of American philosopher John Daniel Wild. In particular, the papers concern Wild's work on aspects of Phenomenology and Existentialism during the last decades of his career.
Wild, John, 1902-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. John Wild, 1975; gift of Richard Sugarman, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
John Daniel Wild (1902-1972)
John Daniel Wild, American philosopher, was born in Chicago, Illinois. He received his B.A. from the University of Chicago and his M.A. from Harvard University. He completed his Ph.D at the University of Chicago in 1926. After teaching for one year at the University of Michigan, Wild joined the Harvard faculty and taught there until 1961.In that year he became chair of the philosophy department at Northwestern University, then a leading center for the study of Phenomenology. He left Northwestern to join the Yale faculty in 1963; his final academic position was with the University of Florida.
His works included Plato's Theory of Man (1946); Plato's Modern Enemies and the Theory of Natural Law (1953); The Challenge of Existentialism (1955); and The Radical Empiricism of William James (1969). Wild was also one of the founders of the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains writings, lecture notes, syllabi, research notes and notebooks and other materials documenting the scholarly career of American philosopher John Daniel Wild. In particular, the papers concern Wild's work on aspects of Phenomenology and Existentialism during the last decades of his career.
Arrangement
Organized in two groupings: I. 1974 Acquisition, 1943-1974; II. 2004 Acquisition, 1934-1972.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. For instance, writings and lecture notes can be found in both groupings. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Christianity and existentialism; Existential phenomenology; Existentialism; Phenomenology; Philosophers -- United States -- Archives; Philosophy, American -- 20th Century; Wild, John, 1902-1972
- 1974 Acquisition, 1943-1974; 4.59; (11 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  Writings, lecture notes, syllabi, research notes and other material documenting the scholarly career of John Daniel Wild.
  Folder titles in quotation marks are transcribed from the original folder labels in the hand of John Daniel Wild. Folders typically contain a variety of material, not all of which may be accounted for in the folder label.
  Former call number: Uncat MS Vault Wild
  - "Philosophy 201b, Spring 1969" (Box 1)
  - "Marxism and Existentialism II", undated (Box 1)
  - "Seminar Yale 1963: Problems of Epistemology and Metaphysics" (Box 1)
  - "Ethics and Political Philosophy", undated (Box 1)
  - "Philosophy of religion, 1967" (Box 1)
  - "Course on Otherness", undated (Box 1)
  - "Ethics and political philosophy", undated (Box 2)
  - "My Book, 1968 Summer!" (Box 2)
  - "Philosophy 255: My Book", undated (Box 2)
  - "Phil. 138b 1960" (Box 2)
  - The Challenge of Existentialism: incomplete draft, undated (Box 2)
  - "My Book: Levels of Awareness", undated (Box 2)
  - "My Book: Subjectiveness", undated (Box 2)
  - "Philosophy 30A: 1965-66", 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - "What I Hold" (parts of APA paper), 1960 (Box 3)
  - Willliam F. Zuurdeeg, "Short paper on methodological points", 1960 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to The Other, including typescript drafts, undated (Box 3)
  - The Other and Otherness, notes and fragments, undated (Box 3)
  - "Talks on Phenomenology and Existentialism", 1957, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Other Person--Some Phenomenological Reflections", undated (Box 3)
  - "My Philosophy ideas", 1957 November; 2 (Box 3)
  - "Preface to Challenge ", 1963; 3 (Box 3)
  - Lecture notes, article notes and bibliography, 1957, undated (Box 3)
  - "Ethics 11b: Secular and Christian ethics", 1956 (Box 4)
  - "The Human Lebenswelt", undated (Box 4)
  - "Poli. Sci. talk, April 9, 1961" (Box 4)
  - The Uses of Philosophy: lecture, undated (Box 4)
  - "Existentialism and Realism:" notes, undated (Box 4)
  - "Philosophy 150, Spring 1954" (Box 4)
  - Notes and drafts on Christianity and Existentialism, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - John Wild bibliography, undated (Box 4)
  - The Death of God and the Life of Man, undated (Box 5)
  - The Rights of the Other as Other, undated (Box 5)
  - "Lecture notes for Philosophy 504", undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - "Projects 1960 ff. Also 1964", undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - The Other Person, undated (Box 5)
  - The World and Its Versions, undated (Box 5)
  - Notes, lecture notes and memoranda, undated; 5 (Box 5)
  - "Collective existences: notes for lecture", undated (Box 5)
  - Existential Themes in the Thought of William James, undated (Box 5)
  - "Notes for Seminar on The A-Priori Philosophy ", 1967 (Box 5)
  - "Notes for Philosophy 56a, Freedom and responsibility", 1966 (Box 5)
  - Unidentified typescript, undated (Box 5)
  - "Popper Paper", 1964 (Box 6)
  - "Work: conference:" papers in several languages, undated (Box 6)
  - "Natural law and personal ethics:" lecture notes, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Review of Being and Nothingness, 1956 (Box 6)
  - "Is Normative Ethics a Rational Discipline?", undated (Box 6)
  - Photocopy of conclusion of unidentified dissertation, undated (Box 6)
  - "Freedom--paper fragments", undated (Box 6)
  - Manuscript and typescript draft of an unidentified history of Western philosophy, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - "A Philosophy of Freedom, Moravian College, 1964" (Box 7)
  - "New MS England 1957:" typescript and manuscript draft (Box 7)
  - "The Thought of William James Today", undated (Box 7)
  - Culture and Barbarism, [1941-1945] (Box 7)
  - Unidentified typescript concerning philosophy, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - "Science of Philosophy--Metaphysics", undated (Box 8)
  - Review of Truth in the Contemporary Crisis, 1942 (Box 8)
  - "A Philosophy of Freedom", undated (Box 8)
  - "Realism and the Existentialist View of War", undated (Box 8)
  - "Man and his Life-world", undated (Box 8)
  - "James: Seminar, Fall 1967" (Box 8)
  - "Feeling: Seminar D10, Fall 1962" (Box 8)
  - "Philosophy of existence: Yale, Fall 1963" (Box 8)
  - "Philosophy 158A 1965-6: Heidigger", 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - "Philosophy 133b: Phenomenology, Spring 1968" (Box 8)
  - "Papers for Florida, 1972" (Box 9)
  - "Phenomenology of belief, Fall 1967" (Box 9)
  - "Existential a priori-final", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Rights of the Other as Other", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Need for a Philosophy of Democracy", 1972 (Box 9)
  - "My Views and Criticisms, 1957" (Box 9)
  - "The World and Its Versions", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Phenomenological Method, 1963-64", 1963-1964 (Box 9)
  - "The Perceptual Time-Lag and Lived Time", 1964 (Box 9)
  - La notion de Lebenswelt chez John Wild, 1967 (Box 9)
  - Tenth Annual Conference on Theology in Action, 1952 (Box 9)
  - "Other materials", undated (Box 10)
  - "Duncan", undated (Box 10)
  - "Existentialism, Feb-March 1951" (Box 10)
  - "Objectivism Geist Hartmann", undated (Box 10)
  - "Colloquium paper Jan 1970" (Box 10)
  - "Notes on new book", undated (Box 10)
  - "The world and its versions, Jan 1964" (Box 10)
  - "The Lived Body", undated (Box 10)
  - "Strasser notes", undated (Box 10)
  - "Eastern Div. Meeting Xmas 1967" (Box 10)
  - "Speeches and sermons, 1960 ff.", [1960s] (Box 10)
  - "Against Utilitarianism, Summer 1960" (Box 10)
  - "Ethics and Politics AMB 1967" (Box 10)
  - "Talks 1969 NY Club: the Life-World and the Other" (Box 10)
  - Offprints, reprints and journal issues, 1943-1974; 4 (Box 11)
- 2004 Acquisition, 1934-1972; 2; (2 boxes)
  Arranged by subject and/or type of material by the donor.
  Notebooks, writings, lecture notes and subject files documenting the scholarly career of John Daniel Wild. Folder titles are derived from the detailed donor list, which is located in Box 12, folder 1.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 733
  - Bibliography of John Wild's Unpublished Writings, by Richard I. Sugarman, undated (Box 12)
    Includes detailed list of the contents of this acquisition.
  - Notebooks, 1934-1938, undated; 6 (Box 12)
    Contents include notes on Aristotle, Hegel and Kant
  - "Papers for Florida", [after 1960]; 5 (Box 12)
    Essays in preparation for publication by Wild. Contents include a draft of Rights of the Other and Existential A Priori.
  - Notes and commentary on E. Levinas, Totality and Infinity, [1969-1970] (Box 12)
  - Lecture notes and commentaries on Phenomenology, undated; 4 (Box 12)
  - Lecture notes and commentaries on Existentialism, undated; 5 (Box 13)
  - Interviews, personal statements and religious talks, undated; 5 (Box 13)
  - Lecture and talk notes, 1960-1963, undated; 6 (Box 13)
  - Subject files, 1952, undated; 4 (Box 13)
  - Eulogy of John Daniel Wild by Henry Jordan, 1972 October 28 (Box 13)
  - Lecture and seminar preparations, 1940-1970; 6 (Box 13)
  - Typescripts and drafts, undated; 4 (Box 13)